Finding Aid for Bernard Isaacs papers, 1919-1981
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Bernard Isaacs papers 1919-1981
Isaacs, Bernard, 1882-1975.
1.3 linear foot
9731 Aa 2
Educator and administrator with the United Hebrew Schools of Detroit, Michigan; writer of short stories, essays, and musical plays. Writings; published works; scattered correspondence relating in part to Detroit Zionism, 1919-1921; miscellaneous relating to the United Hebrew Schools of Detroit; and scores and program to musical plays written by Isaacs, entitled, "Samson and Delilah" and "Saul and David."
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by Ruben H. Isaacs (donor no. 8469 ) in 1996.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Bernard Isaacs was a prominent Jewish educator, scholar and writer. He was born in Lithuania in 1882 and received a traditional Jewish education, concentrating particularly on Hebrew speech and literature. He taught the Hebrew language privately for three years before emigrating to the United States in 1904 to avoid military service in the army of the Czar (whose government he objected to on ethical grounds) before the Russo-Japanese War.
Upon arriving in the United States, Isaacs learned English and earned his Bachelor of Science degree in civil engineering at Cooper Union (1911). After a year as an engineer, he decided to devote his career to Hebrew literature and Jewish education. He taught in New Rochelle and Uptown Talmud Torah, both in New York, before accepting a teaching position in Indianapolis, Indiana, where he eventually became the superintendent of the Hebrew school system. During his stay in Indianapolis, in 1914, he married Belle Ruth Appelbaum of Utica, New York. The Isaacs had four children, Annette, Irving, Ruben Hillel, and Emanuel.
In 1919 Isaacs moved with his family to Detroit, Michigan, where he resided until his death in 1975. He took over the leadership of the newly organized United Hebrew Schools of Detroit in 1919 and remained in that capacity until his retirement in 1955. Under Isaacs's direction, Jewish education in Detroit experienced for the first time a planned curriculum, carefully graded classes and teachers who were trained and experienced. Isaacs emphasized instruction for girls as well as boys and advocated the "Ivrit b'Ivrit" ("Hebrew in Hebrew") method of instruction.
Isaacs was also author of several volumes of short stories written in Hebrew, and often translated in Yiddish and English. Mr. Isaacs died in 1975 at the age of 93.
The collection, a significant portion of which is in Yiddish and Hebrew, consists of a scattering of material over a sixty-year period of time. Of most importance are those files of Isaacs' writings - speeches, short stories, essays and two musical plays (Samson and Delilah and Saul and David) written in Hebrew and given by the pupils of the United Hebrew Schools of Detroit. Except for two volumes of published works, the collection has been arranged alphabetically by topic or type of material.
Subjects:
Isaacs, Bernard, 1882-1975.; Jewish day schools--Michigan--Detroit.; Jews--Michigan--Detroit.; Music--Michigan--Detroit.; United Hebrew Schools of Detroit.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Isaacs, Bernard, 1882-1975.; Murphy, Frank, 1890-1949.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Published books (by and about)
  - Sefer B. Isaacs. Morris Nobel, ed. 1977 (Box 1)
  - Selected Stories. By Bernard Isaacs. Trans. Shoshana Perla. 1968 (Box 1)
- Topical files
  - Biographical information (Box 1)
  - Correspondence 1919-1921, concerning Zionism in Detroit, photocopies (Box 1)
    (In Yiddish)
  - Correspondence 1945-1962 (Box 1)
  - League of Hebrew Writers in Israel (responses of questionnaire (Box 1)
    (in Hebrew)
  - Memorial volume 1975-1978
    - Correspondence
      - Distribution and funding (Box 1)
      - Publications committee (Box 1)
      - Publisher (Box 1)
    - Manuscript and background information (Box 1)
    - News releases and clippings (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous (tributes, United Hebrew Schools materials, etc.) 1944-1981 (Box 1)
  - Periodical clippings 1926-1991
    - English (Box 1)
    - Hebrew and Yiddish (Box 1)
  - Photographs, circa 1915-1975 (Box 1)
  - Reviews of Isaacs's writing 1953-1969 (Box 1)
  - United Hebrew Schools Yiddish lecture notes 1971-1981 (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - "Diary of a Superintendent" (Box 1)
    - "History of the United Hebrew Schools" (Box 1)
    - Literary Reviews (Box 1)
    - Notebooks (Box 1)
    - Short plays (Box 1)
    - Short stories (Box 1)
      (largely in Yiddish and Hebrew)
    - Speeches/lectures (Box 1)
    - Yiddish and Hebrew language materials, 4 folders (Box 1)
    - Musical scores and program
      - Samson and Delilah (Box 2)
      - Saul and David (Box 2)